Richard Hladík

Zürich, CH

+41 76 229 45 30

★ 1997

RichardHladik

(a) rihl@uralyx.cz

A second-semester student of the Computer science MSc programme at ETH Zürich. Theoretical computer scientist at heart, but currently also trying to gain experience in more practical fields, such as ML, bioinformatics, operation research or software engineering. Open source enthusiast. I love pushing the boundaries of human knowledge and creating new and meaningful things, especially in a group of similarly passionate people.



Education

Sept. 2021-Now MSc in Computer science, ETH Zürich (expected graduation: March 2024)

GPA of 5.58 (out of 6.00) after the first semester

SEPT. 2017-June 2021 Bc. in Computer science, Charles University, Prague

perfect grades (GPA of 1.00) throughout the studies and 224 ECTS credits

Experience

Student Researcher (Mar. 2020-Jun. 2021) - Charles University, Prague.

- Algorithm research in **networks flows** and **convex optimisation**. Basis for my bachelor's thesis.
- Closely collaborated with my supervisor. Regularly proposed and disscussed new approaches. Verified our hypotheses and intuitions both theoretically and practially (C++, Python).
- Proposed two **new combinatorial algorithms** for the multicommodity flow (MCF) problem.
- Improved the state of the art convergence for combinatorial MCF algorithms from polynomial to logarithmic for instances with small inflation rate.

Student Researcher (June 2018–Dec. 2020) – Czech Technical University, Praque.

- Optimisation research in **scheduling**.
- Proved NP-hardness of a new periodic scheduling problem, proposed, discussed, developed (C++) and tested several heuristics for it. Wrote auxiliary tools (e.g. instance visualiser) in the process.
- Decreased the approximation error 10 times compared to the base implementation.

Projects

Outotune (Feb. 2020–Now) – a C++ harmoniser implementation.

- Lets you sing harmonies in real time by letting you play chords on your keyboard and synthesising them using your voice.
- Along the way, I increased the performance of an open-source DSP library 3 times by optimising FFT usage and data reuse.

Machine Learning projects (MAR. 2018–DEC. 2022) – Charles University & ETH Zürich

- Various ML projects written in Python (PyTorch and TensorFlow).
- Executed neural network attacks, analysis and adversarial training in a 3-person team.
- Toy ML projects including image segmentation, PoS tagging, speech recognition, 3D object recognition.

Písek (Mar.-May 2020) – a Python framework for the preparation of programming competitions.

- Contributed to the project during the initial phase (was one of the main contributors). I still occasionally help maintain it.
- Added support for the contest format used at the International Olympiad in Informatics.

Operating Systems project (Sept. 2019–Jan. 2020) – a small MIPS OS in C; part of a university course.

• Wrote an OS including interrupt management, heap allocator, scheduler, VM etc. in a two-person team.

Skills

Programming languages: advanced: Python, C++, C, sh; intermediate: SQL; basic: C#, Haskell.

Technologies: Git, NumPy, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Pandas, GoogleTest, GDB, Make. Long-time (> 10 years) Linux user with sysadmin and **systems programming** experience.

I also try to broaden my scope by taking **courses in related areas**. Those include: Computer Linguistics, Deep Learning, Computer Graphics, Data Compression Algorithms, Reliable and Trustworthy AI, Information Theory. Currently I am taking Principles of Distributed Computing.

Languages: Czech (native), English (C2 – CAE Grade A), German (B2–C1), French (basics)

Extracurricular Activities

- 2018–Now Czech Olympiad in Informatics, Czech IOI Selection Camp I implement, test and write up algorithmic tasks; in the latter, I reimplemented and simplified a big part of the technical infrastructure.
- 2017–2020 KSP an algorithmisation correspondence seminar for Czech highschoolers; led the main category in 2018–2019, managing 10–20 people. Co-organised several educational camps with lectures and informatics-related (and -unrelated) activities.

Achievements & Awards

- 2021 ETH-D scholarship for excellent Master's students (≈ 90 out of 2500 students awarded each year)
- 2019 ACM-ICPC Central European Regional Contest 5th place, advanced to World Finals 2020
- 2018 ACM-ICPC World Finals 56th place out of 140 teams
- 2017 International Olympiad in Informatics (IOI) Silver medal, 69th place out of 304 participants
- 2016 ACM-ICPC Central European Regional Contest 12th place (unofficial high school participation)
- 2016 International Olympiad in Informatics (IOI) Bronze medal, 154th place out of 308 participants

Publications

[1] Richard Hladík, Anna Minaeva, and Zdeněk Hanzálek. On the complexity of a periodic scheduling problem with precedence relations. In *International Conference on Combinatorial Optimization and Applications*, page 107–124. Springer, 2020.